<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "AppStream.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<section id="sect-AppStream-ASXML">
	<title>AppStream XML files</title>

	<section id="spec-asxml-introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>

		<para>
			AppStream XML files are small textfiles describing all available applications in the distribution's package repositories.
			The XML files might be compressed with GZip.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="spec-asxml-filenaming">
		<title>File naming and location</title>
		<para>
			The XML files must have an unique name, which is usually the distribution's name and version, combined with the name of the repository/origin.
			For example in Debian 8 (Jessie), the filename for the main repository component would be <filename>debian-jessie-main.xml.gz</filename>.
			For Fedora 20 (Heisenbug) updates it would be <filename>fedora-20-updates.xml.gz</filename>.
			3rd-party repositories use a vendor name and repository-name combination, for example Ubuntu PPAs might get <filename>ppa-ubuntu12.04-username-foobar.xml</filename>.
		</para>
		<para>
			There are two valid locations to store AppStream XML data. <filename>/usr/share/app-info/xmls</filename> stores all AppStream data which
			has been installed via software packages, while <filename>/var/cache/app-info/xmls</filename> stores application data which was downloaded
			by the package manager or placed there by other tools (e.g. Listaller).
			The XML files can either be plain files or be compressed with gzip. It is always a good idea to compress the files, because they tend to become
			quite large.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="spec-asxml-general">
		<title>General XML structure</title>
		<para>
			The XML starts with an <code>&lt;components&gt;</code> tag as root element. It has all the
			<code>&lt;component&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;application&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;font&gt;</code> and
			<code>&lt;inputmethod&gt;</code> elements as children.
		</para>
		<para>
			Data to fill the different component elements is usually taken from their <ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/desktop-entry-spec/latest/">Desktop files</ulink>
			and package data. However, if an upstream project ships metainfo files (see <xref linkend="chap-Metadata"/>),
			values defined there should override data from any other source.
		</para>
		<para>
			All child elements of the <code>&lt;components&gt;</code> element, no matter of which type they are, must at least have
			an <literal>id</literal>, <literal>name</literal>, <literal>summary</literal> and <literal>pkgname</literal> tag.
			For applications, a <literal>icon</literal> tag is also required.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <code>&lt;components&gt;</code> root node has these properties, where the first two are required:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
			<term>version</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This property declares the AppStream spec version this file is based on (currently 0.6). The property is required.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>origin</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Defines the repository-id this AppStream XML file belongs to. This usually matches the filename without extension (see the explanation on how to pick a good filename above).
					It is also used to associate the right cached icons with AppStream metadata. This property is required.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>

	<section id="spec-asxml-tags">
		<title>Valid tags for all component types</title>
		<para>
			These tags can be applied to every component type (application, component, font, inputmethod) which
			is described in the AppStream metadata.
		</para>
		<para>
			Additionally to the <literal>type</literal> property, every <literal>&lt;component/&gt;</literal> tag in AppStream distro data
			may have a <literal>priority</literal> property, defining the priority of this specific metadata over other metadata from different
			AppStream XML files (e.g. from a different repository) which have the same component-id. The value of this tag is an integer, if the
			property is missing, a value of <code>"0"</code> is assumed.
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;id/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The <code>&lt;id/&gt;</code> tag is the same name as the installed .desktop file for the application.
					Additional identifiers are possible later, but right now <literal>desktop</literal> is the only supported type.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;pkgname/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The name of the package which needs to be installed in order to provide this application.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;name/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The application name defined in the application's
						<ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/desktop-entry-spec/latest/">desktop file</ulink>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;project_license/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The <code><![CDATA[<project_license>]]></code> tag is indicating the license of your project/application.
						It should be a string in SPDX format. Licenses may be combined using <emphasis>and</emphasis> and <emphasis>or</emphasis> logic.
						Possible values include:
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>GPL-2.0</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>LGPL-3.0+ and GPL-3.0+</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>MIT</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>CC-BY-SA-2.0</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>...</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
						A full list of recognized licenses and their identifiers can be found at the
						<ulink url="http://spdx.org/licenses/">SPDX OpenSource License Registry</ulink>.
					</para>
					<para>
						Although the license tag is not mandatory, it is recommended to include it.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;summary/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A short summary of the purpose and function of this application. Usually taken from the Desktop file,
						if the application does not ship an AppData file.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;description/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A long description of the application. It is usually taken from the package descriptions or meta-info files, if they were provided.
						The description might use markup. Right now, only paragraph, ordered list and unordered list are supported.
						An example description element might look like this:
						<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<description>
  <p>
   Power Statistics is a program used to view historical and current battery
   information and will show programs running on your computer using power.
  </p>
  <p>Example list:</p>
  <ul>
   <li>First item</li>
   <li>Second item</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
  You probably only need to install this application if you are having problems
  with your laptop battery, or are trying to work out what programs are using
  significant amounts of power.
  </p>
 </description>]]></programlisting>
					</para>
					<para>
						As opposed to the by-paragraph translation used in meta-info files, this tag is translated "as a whole", meaning that the
						<literal>&lt;description/&gt;</literal> tag itself has a language property and contain the translated paragraphs for the given language.
						This allows faster parsing of the Appstream XML file, and does not increase it's size much, as long as it is compressed.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;url/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Defines URLs for this application. This tag can be present multiple times.
					</para>
					<para>
						For a list of possible url types and what they are expected to do,
						take a look at the tag's description at <xref linkend="spec-component-filespec"/>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;project_group/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The <code><![CDATA[<project_group>]]></code> tag identifies a project with a specific upstream umbrella project.
						Known values include <literal>GNOME, KDE, XFCE, LXDE, Mozilla</literal> and <literal>MATE</literal>, although other umbrella projects
						like <literal>Yorba</literal> would make sense too.
					</para>
					<note>
						<para>
							Applications should only identify with an umbrella project if you use all their infrastructure and policies, for instance
							string freezes dates, bugtracker and source control instance.
						</para>
					</note>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;icon/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The <code><![CDATA[<icon>]]></code> tag describes the application's icon.
						It can be of the type <literal>stock</literal>, <literal>cached</literal>, <literal>local</literal>,
						or <literal>url</literal>.
					</para>
					<para>
						<literal>stock</literal> icons are loaded from stock. The icon name should never include any file-extension or path.
					</para>
					<para>
						<literal>cached</literal> icons are loaded from the AppStream icon cache. The icon tag should contain the icon file name, including it's
						extension.
					</para>
					<para>
						<literal>local</literal> icons are reserved for AppStream data installed by local applications or via 3rd-party application installers,
						such as Listaller. They should specify a full file path.
					</para>
					<para>
						<literal>remote</literal> icons loaded from a remote URL. This is currently not implemented anywhere, but might be used in future.
					</para>
					<para>
						Examples of the different methods to specify an icon:
					</para>
					<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<icon type="stock">gimp</icon>
<icon type="cached">firefox.png</icon>
<icon type="local">/usr/share/pixmaps/foobar.png</icon>
<icon type="remote">http://example.com/icons/foobar.png</icon>]]></programlisting>
					<para>
						Multiple <code><![CDATA[<icon/>]]></code> tags might be combined for one application, e.g. to define a <literal>stock</literal> icon
						and a <literal>cached</literal> icon.
						Software-Centers should always prefer the stock icon, if it is available, and fall back to the other icon types if they can not find it.
						The <emphasis>libappstream</emphasis> library makes it easy to do that, if you are not accessing the Xapian database manually.
					</para>
					<para>
						The AppStream Xapian database generator will prefer <literal>cached</literal> over <literal>local</literal> over <literal>remote</literal>
						icons when setting the non-stock icon for the application.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;mimetypes/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This tag can contain one or more <code><![CDATA[<mimetype>]]></code> tags, describing the mime types this application supports.
						The data can usually be fetched from the Desktop files.
						Example:
					</para>
					<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<mimetypes>
    <mimetype>text/html</mimetype>
    <mimetype>image/jpeg</mimetype>
    <mimetype>application/rss+xml</mimetype>
 </mimetypes>]]></programlisting>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;categories/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This tag can contain one or more <code><![CDATA[<category>]]></code> tags, describing the categories this application
						is in.
						This data is usually taken from Desktop files, a list of categories can be found in the
						<ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/menu-spec/latest/apa.html">Freedesktop menu spec</ulink>.
						Example:
					</para>
					<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<categories>
    <category>GNOME</category>
    <category>GTK</category>
    <category>Network</category>
    <category>Telephony</category>
</categories>]]></programlisting>
					<note>
						<title>Deprecated Tags</title>
						<para>
							The tag <code><![CDATA[<appcategories>]]></code> with its <code><![CDATA[<appcategory>]]></code> child elements is deprecated API.
							AppStream parsers should handle these tags just like the <literal>category</literal> tags, there is no difference except for the name.
						</para>
					</note>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;keywords/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This tag can contain one or more <code><![CDATA[<keyword>]]></code> tags, describing keywords for the application,
						to make it easier to find in a software center.
						The data is taken from Desktop files.
						Example:
					</para>
					<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<keywords>
  <keyword>IDE</keyword>
  <keyword>development</keyword>
  <keyword>programming</keyword>
</keywords>]]></programlisting>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;screenshots/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This tag can contain one or more <code><![CDATA[<screenshot>]]></code> tags, describing screenshots which are available for
						the application. A screenshot tag my have the attribute <code>type="default"</code>, marking it as the application's default screenshot,
						which primarily represents it in a software center.
					</para>
					<para>
						Every <code><![CDATA[<screenshot>]]></code> is defined by several images of different sizes.
						All images should have their width and hight set as arguments. Also, one of the images shoukd be marked as <code>type="source"</code>,
						indicating that it is the unscaled version of the screenshot.
						Images of <code>type="thumbnail"</code> define thumbnails of the screenshot.
					</para>
					<para>
						Optionally, a screenshot can contain a <code><![CDATA[<caption>]]></code> tag, describing the screenshot's caption. This is usually what the user can see
						on the image shown. The tag is translatable.
					</para>
					<para>
						Every image should have a full remote url set, usually pointing to a cache of images maintained by the distributor.
						Example:
					</para>
					<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<screenshots>
  <screenshot type="default">
    <caption>Foobar showing kitchen-sink functionality</caption>
    <caption xml:lang="si">Foobar shoeewing kischän-sünk funzionality</caption>
    <image type="source" width="800" height="600">http://www.example.org/en_US/main.png</image>
    <image type="thumbnail" width="200" height="150">http://www.example.org/en_US/main-small.png</image>
  </screenshot>
  <screenshot>
     ....
  </screenshot>
</screenshots>]]></programlisting>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;compulsory_for_desktop/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The <code><![CDATA[<compulsory_for_desktop>]]></code> tag indicates that the application which the data belongs to is essential for the
						functionality of the defined desktop environment. Examples for compulsory applications are the <literal>GNOME-Shell</literal> by the GNOME-Project,
						or the <literal>Plasma-Desktop</literal> by KDE, as well as things like <literal>iBus</literal> or the desktop login manager.
					</para>
					<para>
						Software centers are expected to detect the running desktop environment and disable uninstallation for compulsory components of that desktop,
						so users will not be able to damage their currently running, primary desktop environment.
					</para>
					<para>
						Multiple occurrences of the <code><![CDATA[<compulsory_for_desktop>]]></code> tag are allowed, so a project can be essential for many desktops.
						The distributor decides which applications should be made compulsory, however it is generally a good idea to follow upstream's recommendations on that matter.
					</para>
					<para>
						A list of all allowed values for this tag is defined in the <ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/menu-spec/latest/apb.html">XDG Menu Specification</ulink>.
						Software center applications will only recognize these values.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;provides/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
							This tag is described in detail at <xref linkend="sect-Metadata-GenericComponent"/>.
					</para>
					<para>
						For generic component types, this tag has to be present.
						Distributors must ensure that all things described in this tag are present in the package referenced in
						the associated <literal>pkgname</literal> tag.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;release/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The <code><![CDATA[<release>]]></code> tag describes some metainformation about the current release of the described component.
						It may be present multiple times (for older releases), but a tag for the current version must always be present.
						A <literal>release</literal> tag can have the properties <literal>version</literal> and <literal>timestamp</literal> which contain the version number
						and a release timestamp in form of a UNIX epoch.
					</para>
					<para>
						Examples for a valid release tags:
					</para>
					<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<release version="1.2" timestamp="1397253600" />
<release version="1.0" timestamp="1345932000" />]]></programlisting>
					<para>
						In case a <code>&lt;release/&gt;</code> tag has a <code>&lt;description/&gt;</code> tag as parameter, describing the new release briefly, distributors are encouraged to provide 2-4
						<code>&lt;release/&gt;</code> release tags for every component. If no description is provided, one tag is enough.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>&lt;architectures/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If the <literal>architectures</literal> tag is present, the component is not available on all architectures the distribution supports.
						Supported architectures for this component are specified as children using the <literal>arch</literal> tag.
					</para>
					<para>
						For example, this marks a component to only be available on i686:
					</para>
					<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<architectures>
  <arch>i686</arch>
</architectures>]]></programlisting>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>
	</section>

<!--
	<section id="spec-asxml-tags-font">
		<title>Valid tags for the font component</title>
		<para>
			Additionally to the other components, the <literal>type=font</literal> component knows a few more allowed tags.
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;font_classifier/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Define a description of the font face to caption it when compared against other fonts in the same family.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can find more information about this tag in <xref linkend="spec-fontdata-filespec"/>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;font_parent/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The name of the font package this particular font is part of. This is a required tag.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
-->

	<section id="spec-asxml-example">
		<title>Example file</title>
		<para>
			This is an example AppStream metadata file:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0"?>
<components version="0.6">
  <component type="application">
    <id>firefox.desktop</id>
    <pkgname>firefox-bin</pkgname>
    <name>Firefox</name>
    <name lang="en_GB">Firefoux</name>
    <summary>Web browser</summary>
    <summary lang="fr_FR">Navigateur web</summary>
    <project_license>MPL-2</project_license>
    <keywords>
      <keyword>internet</keyword>
      <keyword>web</keyword>
      <keyword>browser</keyword>
      <keyword lang="fr_FR">navigateur</keyword>
    </keywords>
    <icon type="stock">web-browser</icon>
    <icon type="cached">firefox.png</icon>
    <categories>
      <category>network</category>
      <category>web</category>
    </categories>
    <mimetypes>
      <mimetype>text/html</mimetype>
      <mimetype>text/xml</mimetype>
      <mimetype>application/xhtml+xml</mimetype>
      <mimetype>application/vnd.mozilla.xul+xml</mimetype>
      <mimetype>text/mml</mimetype>
      <mimetype>application/x-xpinstall</mimetype>
      <mimetype>x-scheme-handler/http</mimetype>
      <mimetype>x-scheme-handler/https</mimetype>
    </mimetypes>
    <url type="homepage">http://www.mozilla.com</url>
    <screenshots>
      <screenshot type="default">
        <image type="source" width="800" height="600">http://www.awesomedistro.example.org/en_US/firefox.desktop/main.png</image>
        <image type="thumbnail" width="200" height="150">http://www.awesomedistro.example.org/en_US/firefox.desktop/main-small.png</image>
      </screenshot>
    </screenshots>
    <provides>
      <binary>firefox</binary>
    </provides>
  </component>
  <component>
    <id>pulseaudio</id>
    <name>PulseAudio</name>
    <summary>The PulseAudio sound server</summary>
    <url type="homepage">http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/PulseAudio/</url>
    <project_license>GPLv2</project_license>
    <provides>
      <library>libpulse-simple.so.0</library>
      <library>libpulse.so.0</library>
      <binary>start-pulseaudio-kde</binary>
      <binary>start-pulseaudio-x11</binary>
    </provides>
    <release version="2.0"/>
  </component>
  <component type="font">
    <id>LinLibertine_M.otf</id>
    <name>Libertine</name>
    <summary>Linux Libertine Open fonts</summary>
    <font_classifier>Mono</font_classifier>
    <font_parent>Libertine</font_parent>
  </component>
  <!-- more components here! -->
</components>]]></programlisting>

	</section>
</section>
