<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "AppStream.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<section id="sect-Metadata-GenericComponent">
	<title>Generic Component</title>

	<section id="spec-component-introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			For a distribution, it is good to know more about the content of a package. Which public interfaces (libraries? Python modules?) does it provide? Does it contain codecs? Does it
			contain firmware? Fonts? An application?
			All of this information can be used to automatically install missing software or to offer users a choice on what they want to install from a software center.
		</para>
		<para>
			To provide this information, we created the <emphasis role="italic">metainfo</emphasis> files, which allow <emphasis role="bold">upstream projects</emphasis> to describe the content of their software package.
			If a metainfo file provides a <literal>&lt;provides/&gt;</literal> tag, distributors must also ensure that the package providing the file contain all items referenced
			by that statement, or is installed by a metapackage depending on packages which provide these items. This gives upstream projects a (very light) way to influence distributor packaging.
			More information about that can be found below.
		</para>
		<para>
			Several specialized component-metainfo files exist, for example for applications or fonts. These are all based on this generic component XML specification, and are described in the
			following chapters.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="spec-component-location">
		<title>Filesystem locations</title>
		<para>
			Upstream projects can ship one or more metainfo files in <filename>/usr/share/appdata/%{id}.metainfo.xml</filename>, where <literal>id</literal> is a unique
			identifier of this specific component.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				Applications are a special case here, because they are special in some ways (and also for historical reasons).
				If your metainfo file covers only an application, as described in the AppData section, install it as
				<filename>/usr/share/appdata/%{id}.appdata.xml</filename>.
			</para>
		</note>
		<para>
			Please note that the <filename>/usr/share/appdata/symbols</filename> directory is reserved for a possible future use for storing upstream-generated symbols files for
			libraries.
		</para>
		<important>
			<title>Multiarch Support</title>
			<para>
				On multiarch-aware systems such as Debian: If a component ships a library, the meta-info file should be in the same package as the library itself, or
				in a package depending on that library.
				To make the library packages co-installable, the metadata can be installed into <filename>/usr/share/appdata/&lt;triplet&gt;</filename>, for example
				<filename>/usr/share/appdata/x86_64-linux-gnu/foobar.metainfo.xml</filename>.
				Upstream projects which ship components with libraries should adjust their buildsystem to install a multi-arch compatible metainfo file by default.
				Make use of the <literal>&lt;architectures/&gt;</literal> tag to indicate that the meta-info file is arch specific.
			</para>
		</important>
	</section>

	<section id="spec-component-filespec">
		<title>XML Specification</title>

		<para>
			The XML for a generic component definition starts with an <code><![CDATA[<component>]]></code> tag as root element.
			The <code><![CDATA[<component>]]></code> element must at least have an <literal>id</literal>, <literal>name</literal> and <literal>releases</literal> tag,
			a <literal>provides</literal> tag with appropriate children is highly recommended.
			All possible tags in the generic set are:
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry id="tag-id-generic">
			<term>&lt;id/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The <code language="XML"><![CDATA[<id>]]></code> tag is a short and unique identifier for this component. It must contain only ASCII caracters, dots, hyphens and numbers, spaces are
					not allowed. Specialized metainfo types, such as application or fonts, may apply additional restrictions on the <literal>id</literal> tag value.
				</para>
				<para>
					Note that the value of this tag must be <emphasis>unique</emphasis> across all distributions. In case it is not, distributors are expected to reject the conflicting components
					from inclusion into their metadata.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-metadata_license">
			<term>&lt;metadata_license/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The <code>&lt;metadata_license/&gt;</code> tag is indicating the content licence that you are releasing the one
					Metainfo XML file as. This is not typically the same as the project licence. By ommitting the licence value would
					probably mean your data would not be incorporated into the distribution metadata (so this is a required tag).
					Permissible licence codes include:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>CC0-1.0</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>CC-BY-3.0</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>CC-BY-SA-3.0</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>GFDL-1.3</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>MIT</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					The licence codes correspond to the identifiers found at the <ulink url="http://spdx.org/licenses/">SPDX OpenSource License Registry</ulink>.
					For instance, CC-BY-SA-3.0 corresponds to http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-name">
				<term>&lt;name/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A human-readable name for this software component. For example, if the component id was "libc", it's name might be "GNU Standard C Library".
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-summary">
				<term>&lt;summary/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A short summary of what this component does. If the component is "PackageKit", the summary could be "Provides a package-management abstraction layer".
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-description">
			<term>&lt;description/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					A long description of this component. Some markup can be used.
				</para>
				<para>
					Do not assume the format is HTML. Only paragraph (p), ordered list (ol) and unordered list (ul) are supported at this time.
				</para>
				<para>
					In metainfo files, this tag should be translated by-paragraph, meaning that in a translated file, each translated <literal>&lt;p/&gt;</literal> child
					has a language property.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-url">
				<term>&lt;url/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Defines URLs for this component.There are several different URL types allowed:
					</para>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>homepage</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Should be a link to the upstream homepage for the component.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>bugtracker</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Should point to the software's bug tracking system, for users to report new bugs.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>faq</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Should link a FAQ page for this software, to answer some of the most-asked questions in
									detail, something which you can not do in the component's description.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>help</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>Should provide a link to an online user's reference, a software manual or help page.</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>donation</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Links of this type should point to a webpage showing information on how to donate to
									the described software project.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-releases">
				<term>&lt;releases/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The <code><![CDATA[<releases>]]></code> tag contains <code>&lt;release/&gt;</code> child tags which
						describe some metainformation about the current release of the described software.
						The <code>&lt;release/&gt;</code> tag may be present multiple times (for older releases), but a tag for
						the current version must always be present.
						A <literal>release</literal> tag can have the properties <literal>version</literal> and <literal>timestamp</literal> which contain the version number
						and a release timestamp in form of a UNIX epoch.
					</para>
					<para>
						Examples for a valid releases tag:
					</para>
					<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<releases>
  <release version="1.2" timestamp="1397253600" />
  <release version="1.0" timestamp="1345932000" />
</releases>]]></programlisting>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-provides">
				<term>&lt;provides/&gt;</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The <literal>provides</literal> tag and it's children describe the public interfaces this application provides.
						A public interface can be anything which other applications, which are not part of the upstream project, can access or reference.
						This includes binaries and libraries. Private interfaces should never be added to a <literal>provides</literal> tag.
					</para>
					<para>
						A <literal>provides</literal> tag contain a number of childrens describing the type and name of the provided public interface items.
						It is suggested that the build-system auto-generates this tag and it's children.
						Currently allowed item types are listed below. If you miss something, file a bug against AppStream so we can add the new type.
					</para>

					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>&lt;library/&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Contains the name of a shared library placed in a publicly accessible library path, such as <filename>/usr/lib</filename>, <filename>/usr/lib/&lt;triplet&gt;</filename>
									or <filename>/lib</filename>.
									For example, for the libappstream library, the value for <literal>library</literal> would be <userinput>libappstream.so.1</userinput>.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>&lt;binary/&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Name of a binary installed into a location in <envar>PATH</envar>.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>&lt;font/&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Name of a font provided by this component. For example <userinput>Linux Libertine O</userinput>.
									The tag must have a <literal>file</literal> property stating the filename of the referenced font.
								</para>
								<para>
									Example:
								</para>
								<programlisting language="XML"><![CDATA[<provides>
  <font file="LinLibertine_R.otf">Linux Libertine O</font>
</provides>]]></programlisting>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>&lt;modalias/&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									A modalias glob representing the hardware types (for example USB, PCI, ACPI, DMI) this component handles.
									Useful for installing printer drivers or other USB protocol drivers for smartphones, firmware, kernel drivers which
									are not merged upstream yet or whatever else.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>&lt;firmware/&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Name of the firmware this component provides, to make it possible to find the right firmware package to install for a given kernel driver.
									The value is the path below /lib/firmware to the firmware file in question, like the firmware value exported from Linux kernel modules.
								</para>
								<para>
									Example:
								</para>
								<programlisting language="XML"><![CDATA[<provides>
  <firmware>ipw2200-bss.fw</firmware>
</provides>]]></programlisting>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>&lt;python2/&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Name of a Python2 module this component provides.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

						<varlistentry>
							<term>&lt;python3/&gt;</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Name of a Python3 module this component provides.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>

					</variablelist>
				</listitem>

			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-project_group">
			<term>&lt;project_group/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If you include the <code>&lt;project_group/&gt;</code> tag then this identifies your project with a specific upstream umbrella project.
					Known values include GNOME, KDE, XFCE, MATE and LXDE, although other umbrella projects like Yorba or Mozilla make sense too.
				</para>
				<note>
					<para>
						You should only identify with an umbrella project if you use all their infrastructure and policies, for instance string freezes dates, bugtracker and source control instance.
					</para>
				</note>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry id="tag-screenshots">
			<term>&lt;screenshots/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Visual components (like fonts or graphical applications) may choose to add one or multiple screenshots to their metadata.
				</para>
				<para>
					The <code>&lt;screenshots/&gt;</code> tag contains multiple <code>&lt;screenshot/&gt;</code> childrens, where at least one of them must have the property
					<code>type="default"</code> to indicate the application's primary screenshot. Every <code>&lt;screenshot/&gt;</code> tag must have at least
					one <code>&lt;image/&gt;</code> child, which should define the width and height of the referenced image in it's properties.
					The value of the <code>&lt;image/&gt;</code> tag is a direct URL to a screenshot uploaded to a public location on the web.
				</para>
				<para>
					Optionally, a <code>&lt;screenshot/&gt;</code> tag may have a <code>&lt;caption/&gt;</code> child, defining a short (not more then 255 caracters!)
					description of what the user can see on the referenced screenshot.
				</para>
				<para>
					Ideally, all screenshots should have a 16:9 aspect ratio, and should have a width that is no smaller than 620px.
					They should also be in be in PNG or JPEG format. PNG is the preferred format; JPEG should only be used when screenshots include large photographs or other
					images where a lossy format like JPEG may compress better.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>

		<para>
			An example for a very basic component file could look like this:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component>
  <id>foobar</id>
  <name>Foo Bar</name>
  <summary>A foo-ish bar</summary>
  <url type="homepage">http://www.example.org</url>
  <metadata_license>CC0</metadata_license>

  <provides>
    <library>libfoobar.so.2</library>
    <font>foo.ttf</font>
    <binary>foobar</binary>
  </provides>
  <releases>
    <release version="1.2" timestamp="1365768000" />
  </releases>
</component>]]>
		</programlisting>

	</section>
</section>
