<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "AppStream.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<section id="sect-Metadata-Fonts">
	<title>Fonts</title>

	<section id="spec-fontdata-introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			It is a nice feature for a software center to allows users the installation of additional fonts.
			This meta-info specification describes how metadata about fonts should be structured.
		</para>
		<para>
			Font packages can ship one or more files in <filename>/usr/share/meta-info/%{id}.metainfo.xml</filename>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Font metadata files can - just likle all other metainfo files - be translated. See the section about translation for more information about that.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="spec-fontdata-example">
		<title>Example file</title>
		<para>
			The font meta-info file should look like this:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<font>
  <id type="font">LinLibertine_M.otf</id>
  <metadata_licence>CC0</metadata_licence>
  <name>Libertine</name>
  <summary>Linux Libertine Open fonts</summary>
  <font_classifier>Mono</font_classifier>
  <font_parent>Libertine</font_parent>
</font>]]></programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="spec-fontdata-filespec">
		<title>File specification</title>
		<para>
			Note that the XML root node is <literal>font</literal> now, as opposed to the <literal>component</literal> root node
			in a generic component. This clearly identified this metainfo document as describing a font, instead of a generic software.
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;id/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					For fonts, the <literal>%{id}</literal> is the same name as the installed font file.
					Font packages must set the <literal>type</literal> property of the <literal>id</literal> tag to <code>font</code>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;metadata_licence/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The <code>&lt;metadata_licence/&gt;</code> tag is required. See <xref linkend="sect-Metadata-GenericComponent"/> for a description of this tag.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;name/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Set a name for your font.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;summary/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					A short description of the font described in this metainfo file.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;description/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Add a long description of your font here.
				</para>
				<para>
					Do not assume the format is HTML. Only paragraph, ordered list and unordered list are supported at this time.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;screenshots/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					A screenshot presents your font to the outside world, and could be seen by hundreds or thousands of people.
				</para>
				<para>
					The <code>&lt;screenshots/&gt;</code> tag contains multiple <code>&lt;screenshot/&gt;</code> childrens, where at least one of them must have the property
					<code>type="default"</code> to indicate the application's primary screenshot. Additionally, the <code>&lt;screenshot/&gt;</code> tags should define the width and height
					of the referenced screenshot as properties. The value of these tags is a direct URL to a screenshot uploaded to a public location on the web.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;url/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This is a recommended tag for links of type <code>homepage</code>.
					Links of type <code>homepage</code> should be a link to the upstream homepage for the application.
					See See <xref linkend="sect-Metadata-GenericComponent"/> for a description of this tag.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;provides/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This tag is described for generic components at <xref linkend="sect-Metadata-GenericComponent"/> in detail.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can add one or more children of type <code>&lt;font/&gt;</code> to make the font filenames and names known to the system.
					If this tag is not present, the <literal>name</literal> and <literal>id</literal> tag values will be used by the
					distribution's Appstream-generator to recreate this tag, so it's not required to add it.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;font_classifier/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Define a font class, such as:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Mono</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Serif</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>...</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					TODO: This needs further clarification - what is a classifier? A typeface? font-family? It seems to go beyond that.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
			<term>&lt;font_parent/&gt;</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The name of the font package this particular font is part of. This is a required tag.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

	</section>
</section>
