<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<component type="console-application">
  <id>org.freedesktop.appstream.cli</id>
  <name>AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="ar">شاشة توجيه الأوامر إلى آب-ستريم</name>
  <name xml:lang="bn">অ্যাপস্ট্রিম সিএলআই</name>
  <name xml:lang="bn-BD">অ্যাপস্ট্রিম সিএলআই</name>
  <name xml:lang="ca">Interfície de línia d'ordres d'AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="ckb">دۆخی AppStream:</name>
  <name xml:lang="cs">Textové uživatelské rozhraní pro AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="da">AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="de">AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="en-GB">AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="eo">Komandlinia Interfaco al AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="es">CLI de AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="et">AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="eu">AppStream CLIa</name>
  <name xml:lang="fi">AppStream-komentorivityökalu</name>
  <name xml:lang="fr">Interface en ligne de commande AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="gd">Eadar-aghaidh loidhne-àithne AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="gl">Interface de consola de AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="hi">ऐपस्ट्रीम सीएलआई</name>
  <name xml:lang="hr">AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="hu">AppStream parancssori felület</name>
  <name xml:lang="id">CLI AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="it">CLI AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="ja">AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="ka">AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="ko">AppStream CLI(명령행 인터페이스)</name>
  <name xml:lang="lt">AppStream komandų eilutė</name>
  <name xml:lang="nb">Kommandolinjegrensesnitt for AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="nl">AppStream-CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="oc">Interfàcia en linha de comanda AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="pl">Interfejs AppStream dla wiersza poleceń</name>
  <name xml:lang="pt">Interface de linha de comandos do AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="pt-BR">CLI do AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="ro">CLI AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="ru">Интерфейс командной строки AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="sk">Textové užívateľské rozhranie pre AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="sr">КЛИ за Програмски ток</name>
  <name xml:lang="sr-Latn">CLI za Programski tok</name>
  <name xml:lang="sv">AppStream-CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="tr">AppStream CLI</name>
  <name xml:lang="uk">Командний рядок AppStream</name>
  <name xml:lang="zh-CN">AppStream 命令行界面</name>
  <name xml:lang="zh-TW">AppStream 命令列介面</name>
  <summary>An utility to work with AppStream metadata</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ar">أداة للتعامل مع بيانات AppStream الوصفية</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="bn">অ্যাপস্ট্রিম মেটাডেটা নিয়ে কাজ করার একটি যন্ত্র</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="bn-BD">অ্যাপস্ট্রিম মেটাডেটা নিয়ে কাজ করার একটি যন্ত্র</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ca">Una utilitat per a treballar amb les metadades AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ckb">سوودمەندێکە بۆ کارکردن لەگەڵ مێتاداتای AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="cs">Nástroj pro práci s AppStream metadaty</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="da">Et redskab til at arbejde med AppStream-metadata</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="de">Ein Dienstprogramm zum Arbeiten mit AppStream-Metadaten</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="en-GB">An utility to work with AppStream metadata</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="eo">Ilprogramo por uzi AppStream-metadatenojn</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="es">Una utilidad para trabajar con los metadatos de AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="et">AppStream metaandmetega töötamise utiliit</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="eu">AppStream metadatuekin lan egiteko utilitatea</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="fr">Un utilitaire pour travailler avec les métadonnées AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="gd">Goireas gus obair le meata-dàta AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="gl">Unha utilidade para traballar con metadatos de AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="he">כלי עזר לעבודה עם נתוני העל של AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="hr">Uslužni program za rad s AppStream metapodacima</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="hu">Egy segédprogram az AppStream metaadatokkal való munkához</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="id">Utilitas untuk bekerja dengan metadata AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="it">Uno strumento per lavorare con metadati AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ja">AppStream メタデータを使用して動作するユーティリティー</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ko">AppStream 메타 데이터 작업용 유틸리티</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="lt">Paslaugų programa, skirta darbui su AppStream metaduomenimis</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="nb">Et verktøy for å jobbe med AppStream-metadata</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="nl">Een hulpmiddel om te werken met AppStream-metagegevens</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="oc">Un utilitari per trabalhar amb las metadonadas AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pl">Narzędzie do działania z metadanymi AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pt">Um utilitário para trabalhar com os metadados do AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pt-BR">Um utilitário para trabalhar com os metadados do AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ro">O utilitate pentru a lucra cu datele meta AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ru">Утилита для работы с метаданными AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="sk">Nástroj pre prácu s AppStream metadátami</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="sr">Помагало за рад са метаподацима Програмског тока</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="sv">Ett verktyg för att jobba med AppStream-metadata</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="tr">AppStream üst verileriyle çalışmak için bir araç</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="uk">Інструмент для обробки метаданих AppStream</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="zh-CN">用于操作 AppStream 元数据的实用工具</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="zh-TW">處理 AppStream 中介資料的公用程式</summary>
  <metadata_license>FSFAP</metadata_license>
  <project_license>LGPL-2.1+</project_license>
  <project_group>Freedesktop</project_group>
  <description>
    <p>
      AppStream is a metadata specification which permits software components to provide information about themselves
      to automated systems and end-users before the software is actually installed.
      The AppStream project provides facilities to easily access and transform this metadata, as well as a few additional
      services for building feature-rich software centers and similar applications that make use of software metadata.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="bn-BD">অ্যাপস্ট্রিম হল একটি মেটাডেটা স্পেসিফিকেশন যা কোনও সফ্টওয়্যার চুড়ান্ত ইনস্টল হওয়ার পূর্বে স্বয়ংক্রিয় সিস্টেম এবং ব্যবহারকারীদের কাছে সফটওয়ার উপাদানসমূহকে নিজের সম্পর্কে তথ্য সরবরাহ করার অনুমতি দেয়। অ্যাপস্ট্রিম প্রকল্পটি সহজেই এই মেটাডেটাকে অ্যাক্সেস এবং রূপান্তর করার জন্য সুবিধাসমূহ সরবরাহ করে, পাশাপাশি বৈশিষ্ট্য সমৃদ্ধ সফ্টওয়্যার কেন্দ্রগুলি এবং অনুরূপ অ্যাপ্লিকেশনগুলি তৈরি করার জন্য কয়েকটি অতিরিক্ত পরিষেবা এবং সফ্টওয়্যার মেটাডেটা প্রদান করে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">AppStream és una especificació de metadades que permet als components de programari proporcionar informació sobre si mateixos als sistemes automatitzats i als usuaris finals abans que el programari s'instal·li realment. El projecte AppStream proporciona instal·lacions per a accedir i transformar fàcilment aquestes metadades, així com alguns serveis addicionals per a la construcció de centres de programari rics en funcions i aplicacions similars que fan ús de metadades de programari.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ckb">AppStream تایبەتمەندییەکی میتاداتایە کە ڕێگە بە پێکهاتەکانی نەرمەکاڵا دەدات زانیاری دەربارەی خۆیان بدەن بە سیستەمی ئۆتۆماتیکی و بەکارهێنەرانی کۆتایی پێش ئەوەی نەرمەکاڵاکە بەڕاستی دامەزرێت.  پڕۆژەی ئەپستریم ئاسانکاری بۆ دەستگەیشتن و گۆڕینی ئەم میتاداتایە بە ئاسانی دابین دەکات، هەروەها چەند خزمەتگوزارییەکی زیادە بۆ دروستکردنی سەنتەری نەرمەکاڵا دەوڵەمەند بە تایبەتمەندی و بەرنامەی هاوشێوە کە سوود لە میتاداتای نەرمەکاڵا وەردەگرن.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">AppStream er en metadata-specifikation, der tillader softwarekomponenter at give oplysninger om sig selv til automatiserede systemer og slutbrugere, før softwaren faktisk installeres. AppStream-projektet giver faciliteter til let adgang til og omdannelse af disse metadata samt et par ekstra tjenester til opbygning af funktionsrige softwarecentre og lignende applikationer, der gør brug af softwaremetadata.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">AppStream ist eine Metadatenspezifikation, die es Softwarekomponenten ermöglicht, automatisierten Systemen und Endnutzern Informationen über sich selbst zur Verfügung zu stellen, bevor die Software tatsächlich installiert wird. Das AppStream-Projekt bietet Möglichkeiten, auf diese Metadaten einfach zuzugreifen und sie umzuwandeln, sowie einige zusätzliche Dienste für die Erstellung funktionsreicher Softwarezentren und ähnlicher Anwendungen, die Software-Metadaten nutzen.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en-GB">AppStream is a metadata specification which permits software components to provide information about themselves to automated systems and end-users before the software is actually installed. The AppStream project provides facilities to easily access and transform this metadata, as well as a few additional services for building feature-rich software centres and similar applications that make use of software metadata.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eo">AppStream estas normo pri metadatenoj, kiu ebligas programajn komponantojn informi pri si aŭtomatajn sistemojn kaj uzantojn antaŭ efektiva instalo. La projekto AppStream disponigas ilprogramojn por facile atingi kaj transformi tiujn metadatenojn, kaj ankaŭ kelkajn pliajn servojn por konstrui riĉajn programvendejojn kaj similajn programojn, kiuj uzas metadatenojn pri programoj.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">AppStream es una especificación de metadatos que permite a los componentes de software proporcionar información sobre sí mismos a los sistemas automatizados y a los usuarios finales antes de que el software se instale de forma efectiva. El proyecto AppStream ofrece facilidades para acceder y transformar fácilmente estos metadatos, así como algunos servicios adicionales para construir centros de software con muchas funciones y aplicaciones similares que hagan uso de los metadatos del software.</p>
    <p xml:lang="et">AppStream on metaandmete spetsifikatsioon, mis võimaldab tarkvarakomponentidel anda teavet enda kohta automatiseeritud süsteemidele ja lõppkasutajatele enne tarkvara tegelikku paigaldamist. AppStream-projekt pakub võimalusi, et nendele metaandmetele hõlpsasti ligi pääseda ja neid ümber kujundada, ning pakub ka mõningaid lisateenuseid, mis võimaldavad luua funktsionaalselt rikkalikke tarkvarakeskusi ja sarnaseid rakendusi, mis kasutavad tarkvara metaandmeid.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">AppStream est une spécification de métadonnées qui permet aux composants logiciels de fournir des informations sur eux-mêmes aux systèmes automatisés et aux utilisateurs finaux avant que le logiciel ne soit éventuellement installé. Le projet AppStream fournit des outils pour accéder et transformer facilement ces métadonnées, ainsi que quelques services additionnels pour construire des centres logiciels et assimilés riches en fonctionnalités qui utilisent les métadonnées logicielles.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">AppStream é unha especificación de metadatos que permite que os compoñentes do software proporcionen información sobre eles mesmos aos sistemas automatizados e aos usuarios finais antes de que o software se instale realmente.O proxecto AppStream ofrece facilidades para acceder e transformar facilmente estes metadatos, así como algúns servizos adicionais para construír centros de software ricos en funcións e aplicacións similares que fan uso de metadatos de software.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hr">AppStream je specifikacija metapodataka koja softverskim komponentama omogućuje pružanje informacija o sebi automatiziranim sustavima i krajnjim korisnicima prije nego što se softver stvarno instalira. Projekt AppStream pruža mogućnosti za jednostavan pristup i transformaciju tih metapodataka, kao i nekoliko dodatnih usluga za izgradnju softverskih centara i sličnih programa koji koriste softverske metapodatke.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">Az AppStream egy metaadat-specifikáció, amely lehetővé teszi, hogy a szoftverösszetevők információt szolgáltassanak magukról az automatizált rendszereknek és a végfelhasználóknak még a szoftver tényleges telepítése előtt. Az AppStream projekt lehetőséget biztosít ezen metaadatok egyszerű elérésére és átalakítására, valamint néhány további szolgáltatást a funkciókban gazdag szoftverközpontok és hasonló, a szoftver metaadatait felhasználó alkalmazások létrehozásához.</p>
    <p xml:lang="id">AppStream adalah memungkinkan perangkat lunak memberika informasi tentang diri mereka ke sistem otomatis dan pengguna akhir sebelum benar-benar diinstal. Proyek AppStream menyediakan fasilitas untuk dengan mudah mengakses dan mengubah metadata ini, serta beberapa layanan tambahan untuk membangun pusat perangkat lunak yang kaya fitur dan aplikasi serupa yang memanfaatkan metadata perangkat lunak.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">AppStream è una specifica di metadati che consente ai componenti software di fornire informazioni su se stessi a sistemi automatizzati e utenti finali prima che il software venga effettivamente installato. Il progetto AppStream fornisce strutture per accedere e trasformare facilmente questi metadati, nonché alcuni servizi aggiuntivi per la creazione di software ricchi di funzionalità e di applicazioni che fanno uso di metadati software.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">AppStream은 소프트웨어를 설치하기 전에 소프트웨어 구성 요소에서 자동화된 시스템이나 사용자에게 정보를 제공할 수 있는 메타데이터 표준입니다. AppStream 프로젝트는 이 메타데이터에 쉽게 접근하고 사용할 수 있도록 도와 주며, 다기능 소프트웨어 센터나 소프트웨어 메타데이터를 사용하는 다른 프로그램에 필요한 추가 서비스를 제공합니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nb">AppStream er en metadata-spesifikasjon, som lar programvarekomponenter gi opplysninger om seg selv til automatiserte systemer og sluttbrukere, allerede før programvaren blir installert. AppStream-prosjektet tilbyr funksjonalitet for enkelt tilgang til og mulighet for å omforme disse metadataene.  I tillegg tilbys ekstra tjenester som gjør det mulig å lage programvaresentre og lignende programmer med mye funksjonalitet, ved å bruke de tilgjengelige programvaremetadataene.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">AppStream is een specificatie voor metagegevens waarmee softwarecomponenten informatie over zichzelf kunnen verstrekken aan geautomatiseerde systemen en eindgebruikers voordat de software daadwerkelijk is geïnstalleerd. Het AppStream-project biedt faciliteiten om deze metagegevens gemakkelijk te ontsluiten en te transformeren, alsmede enkele aanvullende diensten voor het bouwen van functierijke softwarecentra en soortgelijke toepassingen die gebruik maken van software-metagegevens.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">AppStream to specyfikacja metadanych umożliwiająca składnikom oprogramowania dostarczanie informacji o sobie zautomatyzowanym systemom i użytkownikom zanim jeszcze zostaną one zainstalowane. Projekt AppStream dostarcza możliwość łatwego używania i przekształcania tych metadanych, a także kilka dodatkowych usług do budowania funkcjonalnych centrów oprogramowania i podobnych programów korzystających z metadanych oprogramowania.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">AppStream é uma especificação de metadados que permite que os componentes de software forneçam informações sobre si mesmos a sistemas automatizados e utilizadores finais antes que o software seja realmente instalado. O projeto AppStream oferece facilidades para acessar e transformar facilmente esses metadados, bem como alguns serviços adicionais para construir centros de software repletos de recursos e aplicações similares que fazem uso de metadados de software.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt-BR">AppStream é uma especificação de metadados que permite que os componentes de software forneçam informações sobre si mesmos a sistemas automatizados e usuários finais antes que o software seja realmente instalado. O projeto AppStream oferece facilidades para acessar e transformar facilmente esses metadados, bem como alguns serviços adicionais para construir centros de software repletos de recursos e aplicativos similares que fazem uso de metadados de software.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">AppStream — это спецификация метаданных, которая позволяет программным компонентам предоставлять информацию о себе автоматизированным системам и конечным пользователям еще до установки программного обеспечения. Проект AppStream предоставляет средства для лёгкого доступа и преобразования этих метаданных, а также несколько дополнительных сервисов для создания многофункциональных программных центров и подобных приложений, использующих метаданные программного обеспечения.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr">Програмски ток је спецификација метаподатака која омогућава софтверским компонентама да пружају информације о себи аутоматизованим системима и крајњим корисницима пре него што се софтвер заиста инсталира. Пројекат Програмског тока пружа могућности лаког приступа и преображаја ових метаподатака, као и неколико додатних услуга за изградњу софтверских центара богатих карактеристикама и сличних апликација које користе софтверске метаподатке.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">AppStream är en metadataspecifikation som låter programvarukomponenter tillhandahålla information om sig själva till automatiserade system och slutanvändare innan programvaran faktiskt installeras. AppStream-projektet tillhandahåller funktionalitet för att lätt komma åt och transformera dessa metadata, såväl som några ytterligare tjänster för att bygga funktionsrika programcentraler och liknande program som drar nytta av programvarumetadata.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">AppStream, yazılım bileşenlerinin, yazılım gerçekten kurulmadan önce otomatik sistemlere ve son kullanıcılara kendileri hakkında bilgi sağlamasına izin veren bir üst veri tanımlamasıdır. AppStream projesi, bu üst verilere kolayca erişmek ve onları dönüştürmek için araçların yanı sıra, zengin özelliklere sahip yazılım merkezleri ve yazılım üst verilerinden yararlanan benzer uygulamalar oluşturmak için birkaç ek hizmet sağlar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">AppStream — специфікація метаданих, за допомогою якої компоненти програмного забезпечення можуть надавати відомості щодо себе автоматизованим система та кінцевим користувачам до встановлення самого програмного забезпечення. У межах проєкту AppStream передбачено засоби для спрощення доступу до метаданих та їхнього перетворення, а також декілька додаткових служб для розширення можливостей центрів керування програмним забезпеченням та подібних програм, які використовують метадані щодо програмного забезпечення.</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh-CN">AppStream 是一种元数据规范，它允许软件组件在实际安装软件之前向自动化系统和最终用户提供有关自身的信息。AppStream 项目提供了方便访问和转换这种元数据的设施，以及一些额外的服务，用于建立功能丰富的软件中心和利用软件元数据的类似应用。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh-TW">AppStream 是中介資料規範，允許軟體組件在實際安裝之前，向自動化系統和終端使用者提供其自身相關資訊。AppStream 專案提供方便存取和轉換這類中介資料的機能，也提供一些額外服務以方便建置功能豐富的軟體中心，或其他利用軟體中介資料的類似應用。</p>
    <p>
      The <em>appstreamcli</em> command-line tool allows to read, write, and transform AppStream XML or YAML metadata
      as well as to validate it for compliance with the specification.
      It also provides easy access to the system metadata pool, for example to query for software that provides a
      specific Mediatype handler or for installing software by its component identifier.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="bn-BD"><em>appstreamcli</em> কমান্ড-লাইন সরঞ্জামটি অ্যাপস্ট্রিম XML বা YAML মেটাডেটা পড়ার, লিখার এবং রূপান্তর করার বৈধতা দেওয়ার পাশাপাশি স্পেসিফিকেশনের সাথে সামঞ্জস্যতা করার অনুমতি দেয়। এটি সিস্টেম মেটাডেটা পুলে সহজে অ্যাক্সেস সরবরাহ করে, উদাহরণস্বরূপ এমন কোনো সফ্টওয়্যার খোঁজার জন্য যা একটি নির্দিষ্ট মিডিয়াটাইপ হ্যান্ডলার সরবরাহ করে অথবা নির্দিষ্ট উপাদান সনাক্ত করার দ্বারা সফ্টওয়্যার ইনস্টল করার জন্য।</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">L'eina de línia d'ordres <em>appstreamcli</em> permet llegir, escriure i transformar metadades APPStream XML o YAML, així com validar-les per al compliment de l'especificació. També proporciona un fàcil accés al conjunt de metadades del sistema, per exemple per a consultar programari que proporciona un controlador de Mediatype específic o per a instal·lar programari pel seu identificador de components.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ckb">ئامرازی هێڵی فەرمانەکانی <em>appstreamcli</em> ڕێگە بە خوێندنەوە، نووسین و گۆڕینی میتاداتای AppStream XML یان YAML دەدات و هەروەها پشتڕاستکردنەوەی بۆ پابەندبوون بە تایبەتمەندییەکە.  هەروەها دەستڕاگەیشتنێکی ئاسان بە مەلەوانگەی میتاداتای سیستەم دابین دەکات، بۆ نموونە بۆ پرسیارکردن بۆ نەرمەکاڵایەک کە مامەڵەکارێکی تایبەتی Mediatype دابین دەکات یان بۆ دامەزراندنی نەرمەکاڵا بە ناسێنەری پێکهاتەکانی.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Kommandolinjeærktøjet <em>appstreamcli</em> gør det muligt at læse, skrive, validere og transformere AppStream XML- eller YAML-metadata samt validere den for overholdelse af specifikationen. Det giver også let adgang til systemets metadatasamling, f.eks. til at forespørge software der håndtere en bestemt MIME-type eller for at installere software med dens komponentidentifikator.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">Das Kommandozeilen-Werkzeug <em>appstreamcli</em> ermöglicht das Lesen, Schreiben und Umwandeln von AppStream XML- oder YAML-Metadaten sowie deren Validierung auf Übereinstimmung mit der Spezifikation. Es bietet außerdem einen einfachen Zugriff auf den System-Metadaten-Pool, um z. B. nach Software zu suchen, die einen bestimmten Mediatype-Handler bereitstellt, oder um Software anhand ihres Komponenten-Identifikators zu installieren.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en-GB">The <em>appstreamcli</em> command-line tool allows reading, writing, and transforming AppStream XML or YAML metadata as well as validating it for compliance with the specification. It also provides easy access to the system metadata pool, for example to query for software that provides a specific Mediatype handler or for installing software by its component identifier.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eo">La komandlinia ilprogramo <em>appstreamcli</em> ebligas legi, skribi, kaj transformi XML- aŭ YAML-metadatenojn de AppStream kaj ankaŭ validigi ĝin pri kongruado kun la normo. Ĝi ankaŭ ebligas facile atingi la sisteman metadatenaron, ekzemple por serĉi programon, kiu disponigas pritraktilon de specifa aŭdvidaĵa tipo, aŭ por instali programan komponanton per ĝia identigilo.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">La herramienta de línea de comandos <em>appstreamcli</em> permite leer, escribir y transformar los metadatos XML o YAML de AppStream, así como validar su cumplimiento con la especificación. También proporciona un fácil acceso al conjunto de metadatos del sistema, por ejemplo para consultar el software que proporciona un manejador Mediatype específico o para instalar software por su identificador de componente.</p>
    <p xml:lang="et">Käsurea tööriist <em>appstreamcli</em> võimaldab lugeda, kirjutada ja teisendada AppStream XML- või YAML-metaandmeid ning kontrollida nende vastavust spetsifikatsioonile. Samuti võimaldab see lihtsat juurdepääsu süsteemi metaandmete kogule, näiteks konkreetse Mediatype'i käsitsitajat pakkuva tarkvara päringu tegemiseks või tarkvara paigaldamiseks selle komponendi identifikaatori järgi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">L’outil en ligne de commande <em>appstreamcli</em> permet la lecture, l’écriture, la validation et la transformation des métadonnées XML ou YAML d’AppStream. Il fournit également un accès aisé au pool de métadonnées système pour, par exemple, chercher un logiciel qui fournit un gestionnaire de type de média spécifique ou en installer un en utilisant son identifiant de composant.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">A ferramenta de liña de comandos <em>appstreamcli</em> permite ler, escribir e transformar metadatos XML ou YAML de AppStream, así como validalos para que cumpran coa especificación.Tamén proporciona un acceso sinxelo ao grupo de metadatos do sistema, por exemplo para consultar o software que proporciona un controlador de Mediatype específico ou para instalar software mediante o seu identificador de compoñente.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hr">Alat <em>appstreamcli</em> omogućuje čitanje, pisanje, provjeru ispravnosti i transformaciju AppStream XML ili YAML metapodataka. Također daje pristup sabiralištu metapodataka sustava, na primjer, za traženje softvera koji pruža određenu MIME vrstu ili za instaliranje pomoću njenog identifikatora komponenata softvera.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">Az <em>appstreamcli</em> parancssori eszköz lehetővé teszi az AppStream XML vagy YAML metaadatok olvasását, írását és átalakítását, valamint a specifikációnak való megfelelésük ellenőrzését. Emellett egyszerű hozzáférést biztosít a rendszer metaadat-tárolójához, például egy adott médiatípus-kezelőt biztosító szoftverek lekérdezéséhez vagy a szoftverek telepítéséhez az összetevő-azonosítójuk alapján.</p>
    <p xml:lang="id"><em>appstreamcli </em> memungkinkan pembacaan, penulisan, validasi, dan transformasi metadata XML atau YAML AppStream. Ini memberi akses ke pool metadata sistem untuk misalnya mengkueri perangkat lunak yang menyediakan MIME-type tertentu dan memasangnya dengan identifier komponen perangkat lunaknya.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">Il programma <em>appstreamcli</em> consente di leggere, scrivere, validare e trasformare metadati AppStream XML o YAML. Consente inoltre di accedere all'insieme dei metadati del sistema allo scopo, per esempio, di eseguire ricerche su un software che fornisce uno specifico tipo di MIME e installarlo attraverso il suo identificativo.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko"><em>appstreamcli</em> 명령줄 도구를 사용하면 AppStream XML 또는 YAML 메타데이터를 읽고, 쓰고, 변환하고 사양 준수 여부를 확인할 수 있습니다. 또한 예를 들어 특정 Mediatype 핸들러를 제공하는 소프트웨어를 쿼리하거나 구성 요소 식별자로 소프트웨어를 설치하기 위해 시스템 메타데이터 풀에 쉽게 액세스할 수 있습니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nb">Kommandolinjeverktøyet <em>appstreamcli</em> tillater lesing, skriving og godkjenning av transformering av AppStream sin XML- eller YAML-metadata. Det gir også tilgang til systemets metadatagrunnlag, for eksempel for spørringer til programvare som tilbyr en spesifikk MIME-type, og installasjon av dens programvarekomponentidentifikator.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Met de opdrachtregel-tool <em>appstreamcli</em> kunt u AppStream-metagegevens in XML- of YAML-formaat lezen, schrijven en omzetten, en deze valideren op overeenstemming met de specificatie. Het biedt ook gemakkelijk toegang tot de metagegevens-pool van het systeem, bijvoorbeeld om te zoeken naar software die een specifieke Mediatype-handler biedt of om software te installeren op basis van de componentidentificatie.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">Narzędzie wiersza poleceń <em>appstreamcli</em> umożliwia odczytywanie, zapisywanie i przekształcanie metadanych AppStream w językach XML i YAML, a także sprawdzanie ich zgodności ze specyfikacją. Umożliwia także łatwy dostęp do puli metadanych systemu, aby na przykład wyszukać oprogramowanie dostarczające obsługę podanego typu multimediów lub zainstalować oprogramowanie według jego identyfikatora składnika.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">A ferramenta da linha de comandos <em>appstreamcli</em> permite ler, escrever, e transformar metadados AppStream em XML ou YAML, bem como validá-la para conformidade com a especificação. Esta também permite aceder ao grupo de metadados do sistema, por exemplo, consultar por um "software" que forneça um tipo MIME específico, ou para instalar "software" usando o próprio identificador de componente.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt-BR">Esta ferramenta de linha de comando <em>appstreamcli</em> permite ler, escrever e transformar metadados AppStream em XML ou YAML, bem como validá-los para conformidade com a especificação. Também permite acessar o pool de metadados do sistema para, por exemplo, consultar por um software fornecendo um manipulador de tipo de mídia específico e instalar o software usando o identificador de seu componente.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">Инструмент командной строки <em>appstreamcli</em> позволяет читать, записывать и преобразовывать метаданные AppStream XML или YAML, а также проверять их на соответствие спецификации. Он также обеспечивает лёгкий доступ к пулу метаданных системы, например, для запроса программного обеспечения, предоставляющего определенный обработчик Mediatype, или для установки программного обеспечения по идентификатору компонента.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr">Алат линије наредби „<em>appstreamcli</em>“ омогућава читање, писање и преображај „XML“ или „YAML“ метаподатака Програмског тока, као и потврђивање њихове усклађености са спецификацијом. Такође пружа једноставан приступ системском спремишту метаподатака, на пример, за упит за софтвер који пружа одређени обрађивач врсте медија или за инсталирање софтвера помоћу његовог одредника компоненте.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">Kommandoradsverktyget <em>appstreamcli</em> möjliggör läsning, skrivning och transformering av AppStream XML- eller YAML-metadata samt att validera att det stämmer mot specifikationen. Det ger också enkel åtkomst till systemmetadatapoolen för att till exempel söka efter program som innehåller en specifik Mediatype-hanterare eller för att installera programvara med dess komponentidentifierare.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr"><em>appstreamcli</em> komut satırı aracı, AppStream XML veya YAML üst verilerinin okunmasına, yazılmasına ve dönüştürülmesine ve ayrıca tanımlamayla uyumluluğunun doğrulanmasına izin verir. Ayrıca, örneğin belirli bir Mediatype işleyicisi sağlayan yazılımı sorgulamak veya bileşen tanımlayıcısıyla yazılım yüklemek için sistem üst veri havuzuna kolay erişim sağlar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">За допомогою <em>appstreamcli</em> можна читати, записувати, перевіряти та перетворювати метадані AppStream у форматах XML і YAML, а також перевіряти ці метадані на відповідність специфікації. Також за її допомогою можна отримувати доступ до буфера загальносистемних метаданих, наприклад, для того, щоб визначити програмне забезпечення для обробки даних певного мультимедійного типу або щоб встановити програмне забезпечення за ідентифікатором його компонента.</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh-CN"><em>appstreamcli</em> 命令行工具允许读取、写入和转换 AppStream XML 或 YAML 元数据，并验证其是否符合规范。它还提供了对系统元数据池的简单访问，例如查询提供特定 Mediatype 处理程序的软件，或者通过组件标识符安装软件。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh-TW"><em>appstreamcli</em> 指令列工具可以讀寫與變換 AppStream XML 或 YAML 中介資料，以及驗證資料是否遵循規範。此外它還能輕鬆存取系統中介資料池，以搜尋諸如提供某特定媒體類型處理器使用的軟體，或是按照軟體的組件辨識碼進行安裝等。</p>
  </description>
  <url type="homepage">https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Distributions/AppStream/</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/ximion/appstream/issues</url>
  <url type="help">https://www.freedesktop.org/software/appstream/docs/chap-AppStream-ManualPages.html</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/ximion/appstream/</url>
  <provides>
    <binary>appstreamcli</binary>
  </provides>
  <translation type="gettext">appstream</translation>
  <releases>
    <release type="stable" version="0.16.2" date="2023-04-26T00:00:00Z">
      <description>
        <p>Due to a past mistake, AppStream until now assumed xml:lang was using POSIX locale, while in fact XML locale need to be in BCP47 format. Most of the translation tools do this correctly, but notably msgfmt when used in batch mode doesn't</p>
        <p>This release adds the following features:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Add API for asking whether the pool is empty</li>
          <li>Add DDE to known desktop-environment list</li>
          <li>validator: Check if Release Description is inside description tag</li>
          <li>Make AppStream use BCP47 for locale in XML data</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release fixes the following bugs:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Add missing standard::is-hidden attribute to file search enumerator</li>
          <li>spdx: Accept brackets in spdx license expression check</li>
          <li>introspection: Bring back AS_FORMAT_STYLE_COLLECTION into its enum</li>
          <li>compose: Fix crash in asc_l10n_search_translations_qt()</li>
          <li>compose: Set lower-cased CID for synthesized components again</li>
          <li>Don't crash when non-YAML documents are read as YAML</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release includes the following change:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>sanitizers: Allow null-dereference check again</li>
        </ul>
        <p>With contributions from:</p>
        <p>Aleix Pol, Caolán McNamara, Corentin Noël, Gary Wang,
 Gleb Popov, JakobDev, Matthias Klumpp, Will Thompson</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release type="stable" version="0.16.1" date="2023-02-10T00:00:00Z">
      <description>
        <p>This is a bugfix-only release to primarily address an issue introduced in v0.15.6 that caused any clients using GIR bindings to crash after a while.</p>
        <p>This release updates documentation:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>docs: Clarify the locations where catalog icons should be placed</li>
          <li>spec: Expand documentation for &lt;issue&gt; elements</li>
          <li>spec: Mention that &lt;issues&gt; is not part of the description</li>
          <li>spec: Give some guidance about tone in release descriptions</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release fixes the following bugs:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fix binding helper macro to behave correctly if a function is passed directly</li>
          <li>Override-merge icons and provided items correctly</li>
          <li>tests: Ensure locale is C.UTF-8 in pool tests</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release includes the following change:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>release: Add sanity checks at beginning of each function</li>
        </ul>
        <p>With contributions from:</p>
        <p>Corentin Noël, Matthias Klumpp, Pablo Correa Gómez, Philip Withnall</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release type="stable" version="0.16.0" date="2023-01-26T00:00:00Z">
      <description>
        <p>This release adds the following features:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>pool: Offer API to look up components by bundles</li>
          <li>Bump format version to 0.16</li>
          <li>Add new AsSystemInfo to read information about the current OS and device</li>
          <li>Add helper to get device names from a modalias</li>
          <li>Implement support for external release metadata</li>
          <li>Add validation support for external release metadata</li>
          <li>compose: Validate external release metadata used for the catalog as well</li>
          <li>its: Add rule for standalone release metadata</li>
          <li>Add function to test if an AsRelation is satisfied on the current system</li>
          <li>cli: Add command to list category contents</li>
          <li>cli: Display colored checkmarks if possible</li>
          <li>cli: Add new is-satisfied check to test relations from the command-line</li>
          <li>cli: Add Markdown export support for metainfo-to-news</li>
          <li>qt: Add support for SystemInfo &amp; relation satisfication checks</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release updates documentation:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>spec: Specify a metadata format for external release descriptions</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release fixes the following bugs:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fix build with Clang 15</li>
          <li>Give a better error message if trying to list too many categories</li>
          <li>Adjust documentation of AsPool.get_components_by_categories to reflect reality</li>
          <li>validator: Validate merge component catalog data properly again</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release includes the following change:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Consistently name catalog metadata as such everywhere</li>
        </ul>
        <p>With contributions from:</p>
        <p>Aleix Pol, Matthias Klumpp, Rafael Fontenelle</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release type="stable" version="0.15.6" date="2022-12-22T00:00:00Z">
      <description>
        <p>This release adds the following features:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>qt: Add API for ContentRating descriptions and ratingIds</li>
          <li>Add some coccinelle semantic patches for common style issues</li>
          <li>compose: Allow building without SVG support</li>
          <li>validator: Check for nodes that are text nodes even though they shouldn't be</li>
          <li>validator: Extend validation for custom tag</li>
          <li>validator: Improve Screenshot validation</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release updates documentation:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>docs: Fix typos in &lt;extends&gt; documentation</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release fixes the following bugs:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>validator: internat: Don't allow bandwidth_mbitps when value is offline-only</li>
          <li>validator: Fix timestamp validation</li>
          <li>validator: Allow release descriptions to start with punctuation</li>
          <li>compose: Only add no-metainfo tag if component isn't already ignored</li>
          <li>compose: Show better error in AscImage if compose was build without rsvg</li>
          <li>Add a hack to clarify proper PtrArray element ownership for language bindings</li>
          <li>qt: Port away from deprecated QDateTime API</li>
          <li>qt: Deprecate Component::requires</li>
          <li>qt: Fix warning</li>
          <li>qt: Fix stringListToCharArray and Pool::componentsByCategories</li>
          <li>qt: Port away from deprecated foreach</li>
          <li>as-review: Add a typedef for property enums</li>
          <li>as-review: Install properties at once rather than individually</li>
          <li>as-review: Specify G_PARAM_STATIC_STRINGS for properties</li>
          <li>as-review: Emit GObject::notify on property value changes</li>
          <li>as-review: Add missing property for as_review_{get,set}_priority()</li>
          <li>ascli: fix NULL pointer dereference</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release includes the following changes:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>docs: Split releases specification into its own section</li>
          <li>style: Make code easier to read by using helper macros in all places</li>
          <li>Make some compiler warnings fatal unconditionally</li>
        </ul>
        <p>With contributions from:</p>
        <p>Aleix Pol, JakobDev, Matthias Klumpp, Nicolas Fella, Philip Withnall,
 r-ricci, Will Thompson</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release type="stable" version="0.15.5" date="2022-08-22T00:00:00Z">
      <description>
        <p>This release adds the following features:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>validator: Allow severity downgrade of releases-not-in-order for GNOME</li>
          <li>validator: Perform stricter integer validation</li>
          <li>validator: Check for url redefinitions</li>
          <li>Implement the "replaces" tag</li>
          <li>Add convenience function that check if component is free by license and origin</li>
          <li>qt: Add wrappers for AsComponent isFree/supports/replaces</li>
          <li>Always add untranslated component names to the search index</li>
          <li>validator: Validate the "internet" relation item</li>
          <li>validator: Add validation for memory relation</li>
          <li>Implement internet relation item</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release updates documentation:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>spec: Specify a proper "replaces" tag</li>
          <li>spec: Add an &lt;internet/&gt; kind to requires/recommends/supports</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release fixes the following bugs:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>validator: Don't permit overriding the unknown root tag issue</li>
          <li>compose: Don't crash if metainfo file contains an invalid stock icon</li>
          <li>spdx: Fix possible crash when NULL is passed to is_free_license</li>
          <li>compose: Don't synthesize components for desktop files of settings apps</li>
          <li>Return the correct values in as_display_length_kind_from_px()</li>
          <li>validator: Distinguish translatable from not-translatable tags in duplicate checks</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release includes the following changes:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Silence static analyzer false-positives based on GCC version</li>
          <li>data: use lxml to get the XDG categories</li>
        </ul>
        <p>With contributions from:</p>
        <p>JakobDev, Philip Withnall, Pino Toscano, Matthias Klumpp</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release type="stable" version="0.15.4" date="2022-05-22T00:00:00Z">
      <description>
        <p>This release adds the following features:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>validator: Check timestamp validity</li>
          <li>validator: Allow</li>
          <li>validator: Add strict mode</li>
          <li>ascli: validate: Allow simple overriding of issue tags</li>
          <li>validator: Check for exact relation item redefinitions</li>
        </ul>
        <p>This release fixes the following bugs:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Add vcs-browser URL to metainfo.xml</li>
          <li>compose: Improve media-baseurl sanity checks for icon/screenshot policies</li>
          <li>compose: Don't create bad data when localized screenshots exist</li>
          <li>compose: Sanitize prefix value and verify all units for results</li>
          <li>compose: Fail and not just warn if we couldn't open a unit</li>
          <li>compose: Make no-result detection a bit more robust</li>
          <li>compose: Properly handle localized screenshots</li>
          <li>compose: Ignore current locale when analyzing screencasts</li>
        </ul>
        <p>With contributions from:</p>
        <p>JakobDev, Matthias Klumpp</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1"/>
</component>
