<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "AppStream.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<section id="sect-AppStream-Specs-AppData">
	<title>AppData XML files</title>

	<section id="spec-appdata-introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			Every software center that exists allows the user to look at screenshots and a long description of the application before it is installed.
			For most users it allows them to answer the question <quote>Do I want to install this application?</quote>.
			Traditionally in Linux distributions, we have none of this data for the vast majority of our desktop user-installable applications.
			The packages-descriptions are describing all contents of a package, and not just a single application. They are also often written in a technical
			language and refer to other packages, which makes it hard for beginners to understand what the application they want to install really does.
			Additionally, if you are not using Debian or Ubuntu, the package descriptions are often untranslated.
			Also, packages do not provide some metadata users might be interested in before installing an application.
		</para>
		<para>
			To solve this, we have defined a new data file, which the upstream project can optionally translate using the same technique as
			<ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/desktop-entry-spec/latest/">Desktop files</ulink> or GSetting schemas.
			The AppData specification is a subset of the AppStream metadata (see <xref linkend="sect-AppStream-Specs-ASXML"/>).
		</para>
		<para>
			The AppData files override any values which are automatically fetched by the AppStream data generator.
			Applications can ship one or more files in <filename>/usr/share/appdata/%{id}.appdata.xml</filename>.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="spec-appdata-filespec">
		<title>File specification</title>

		<para>
			The file should contain something like this:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="XML">
<![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application>
 <id type="desktop">gnome-power-statistics.desktop</id>
 <licence>CC0</licence>
 <name>Power Statistics</name>
 <summary>Observe power management</summary>
 <description>
  <p>
   Power Statistics is a program used to view historical and current battery
   information and will show programs running on your computer using power.
  </p>
  <p>Example list:</p>
  <ul>
   <li>First item</li>
   <li>Second item</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
  You probably only need to install this application if you are having problems
  with your laptop battery, or are trying to work out what programs are using
  significant amounts of power.
  </p>
 </description>
 <screenshots>
  <screenshot type="default" width="800" height="600">http://www.hughsie.com/en_US/main.png</screenshot>
  <screenshot width="800" height="600">http://www.hughsie.com/en_US/preferences.png</screenshot>
 </screenshots>
 <url type="homepage">http://www.gnome.org/projects/en_US/gnome-power-manager</url>
 <updatecontact>gnome-power-manager-list@gnome.org</updatecontact>
 <project_group>GNOME</project_group>
</application>]]>
		</programlisting>

	</section>
</section>
